It’s crazy when you think about all of
the different kinds of foods we eat.
We just swallow and hope
it all works out for the best.
Well, as it turns out,
there are better ways to think about keeping
our bodies humming healthfully along.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we answer a wide
variety of your questions, like...
the importance of a
good breakfast smoothie,
what kind of scientific study
I’d like to see performed,
and we start with an interesting
question from Keene
about whether there
have been any updates
on the therapeutic
use of psychedelics.
So psychedelics was on my list of topics.
It's so fascinating, such an incredible area.
There's finally been some placebo-controlled
trials. You say, “Wait a second, how do you
do a placebo-controlled trial?” Right? You kind of
notice when you're on mushrooms or whatever. But
no—how about we anesthetize people, make people
unconscious, then give them mushrooms or not.
They have no idea when they wake up afterwards
whether they were on mushrooms or not. Does it
actually change the brain? Does it actually do
anything? Or do you actually need to have that
component? So many interesting questions. I
wanted to do a deep dive. There's the whole
ketamine stuff. And I really wanted to cover it
all. Is MDMA going to hurt our brains? And just
so many questions I just don't know the answers
to, and I was eager to find out. I get a lot of
questions about it. So I got about 300 meg worth
of PDFs, a couple hundred articles on ayahuasca,
LSD, mescaline, microdosing—talk about safety.
So I have the research. It's there. I just have
to read it and write it. And unfortunately, it
all fell down before I was able to jump on it.
Any data—this is actually something I looked into.
This is what do they call it? It's not a seaweed.
It actually grows on the shores in brackish water.
So it pulls up salt. So it's like this salty moss
or something, this plant that has a high salt
content. And so it's a way to add salt to a food
secretly. Pickleweed. Anyway, there was a whole
food plant-based muffin mix company that—like,
well, wait a second. How do you have
a whole food plant-based muffin? Well,
what can you use for sweetener? You use date
powder, right? Whole food. But what do you use
for salt? Anyone who's baked knows you add salt
to baked goods to change the flavor profile.
If it's whole food plant-based, there can't
be any salt in it. And so what they used is
this ingredient. And so I was like, “Oh, all
right. Well, let's look it up.” And so they're
effectively just adding salt. I forget—it's like
30% of the weight of this plant is pure salt. It
just sucks up the salt from the seawater. And so,
I mean, look at the sodium. It's off the charts,
as you'd expect, as if you just added
salt. So it's kind of a sneaky way.
And so I contacted them. I was like, you can't do
this. You can't get away with this. And so they
actually changed it to potassium chloride, which
is the way to do it. You move from sodium salt to
potassium salt. So that's the way you can actually
cut down on sodium. So I would not eat this really
salty plant, even though it's like a whole food,
right? But it's too much sodium. If you want your
food salty, use potassium chloride, or season
it in a way where you don't need it so salty.
Tyler says, “If I make a smoothie
with 80% of my vitamin mineral intake,
it will absorb the nutrients that I need.”
Well, I mean, it depends on your vitamin
mineral status. Your body actually—if you're
low on calcium, your body absorbs more calcium.
If you're low on iron, your body absorbs more
iron. And vice versa: if you have too much iron,
your body actually doesn't want too much and so
puts the brakes on. I mean, if you had one meal
a day that had 100% of your nutrient needs,
you would stay alive. I mean, you don't have
to split it up through the day. Your body would
probably, the first day, be like, whoa—one meal,
we got all this manganese or whatever. But it'll
eventually get to be like, oh, I guess that's what
we're doing these days: one meal a day. And so I
gotta take my entire manganese allotment in this
one meal, and it'll do it. Our body's pretty
smart. So yeah, I wouldn't worry about it.
In fact, I think for a lot of people, the
breakfast smoothie is probably the healthiest
meal of the day. That's one of the great things
about smoothies—you can add all sorts of noxious
stuff. My smoothie this morning had so many
broccoli sprouts it was almost too much. I've
been trying to experiment with adding more
and more broccoli sprouts, and I was like,
I don't taste them at all. It's amazing,
right? You mix it with the berries and you
just don't taste the broccolininess at all. Okay,
you do. Today was the first day I was like, “Okay,
my smoothie tastes like broccoli.” But it was a
lot of broccoli sprouts, right? I would not want
to eat that many broccoli sprouts throughout the
day because it has a really kind of spicy flavor,
or radishy bite to it. So you make a smoothie,
you could add all sorts of greens and the amla
and stuff that's just normally nasty. So
you could have just so much nutrition,
and then even if you falter later in the day, at
least you got a good solid, solid, solid base.
So I'm down with that strategy. Although
tomorrow I'm adding less broccoli sprouts.
Let me see. HG. Oh, what am I eating today?
So this morning I had my sprout disaster. So
you make your own sprouts—broccoli sprouts.
Super easy to make. I think it's 25 cents
per cup. Sprout them yourselves.
So on a nutrition-per-dollar basis,
probably impossible to beat. I mean,
maybe a good sweet potato comes close,
but it's pretty amazing. So anyway, the list of
stuff I have in my smoothie would take all day.
But for lunch, I had leftovers.
I knew I had 14 interviews today,
so I didn't have time to actually make food. And
so I had leftovers of a wonderful spaghetti sauce
packed with veggies. Got some artichoke hearts
in there. And so I had that on some whole wheat
spaghetti. And then for supper, I'm going to
do purple sweet potato fries. And then I don't
know what else, but I'm excited for my purple
sweet potato fries. They're so hard to find in
rural Virginia. Not all of us can live in big
fancy cities, but I finally found a source of
purple sweet potatoes. I haven't had them in a
while, so I'm super excited to make some fries.
Anyway, all right. Next up, Silly Head—not one,
not two, but Silly Head Five—says, “If I could
see one study get performed, what would I want
to see put to the test?” I'm a big fan. Well,
so there are studies that would be really useful
and interesting scientifically, but ultimately
it's all about making people's lives better.
And so those are kind of two different things.
In terms of having an actual impact on the
world, it would probably be a disease reversal
study. I mean, that excites people. You do
some basic science thing which unveils some
really interesting thing about some random
enzyme—maybe in 20 years that does something
interesting to help people—but if you want
the kind of bang for your buck right now,
I've been working on How Not to Hurt, this pain
management book through lifestyle. And there's
this series of amazing studies called Plants for
Joints on osteoarthritis and rheumatoid arthritis,
randomizing people to a whole food plant-based
diet and seeing remarkable benefits. And
osteoarthritis is the leading cause of physical
disability among older men and women. The fact
that you can so improve pain and function just
by changing people's diets—that is so cool.
And so those are the kind of studies
I would like to see, where people,
within a matter of weeks, change their
diet and not just their lab values change,
but their day-to-day function changes. They
can go up and downstairs without hurting.
They can play with their grandkids more. And it's
super common—not some rare little niche disease.
So I'd love to see—how about back pain
studies? There haven't been any—oh,
actually, I take that back. There haven't
been any plant-based dietary intervention
studies for back pain, but I was about to say
there haven't been any randomized controlled
dietary trials for back pain. There actually
were. I think there was a Mediterranean one.
Anyway, I'd like to see plant-based, since
blood flow through the vertebral arteries
may indeed play a role in certain types of
low back pain. It would be nice to see if
you actually improve that circulation, would you
actually see some benefit? That hasn't been done.
So yeah—disease reversal studies, common chronic
disease reversal studies, that can excite the
imagination, grab headlines, and get people
thinking—particularly physicians thinking, wow,
I have a hundred people in my practice with the
exact same condition. That's really frustrating
to treat. I can't make them better. Every time
they come to the office, I wish I could give them
something. But what am I going to do—give them
another opioid prescription or something? No.
Now all of a sudden there's a tool to actually
make people feel better. That's amazing.
So that's the kind of study I would do.
And unfortunately, we're out of time.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
As always, all proceeds from
book sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.